<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The English Episcopacy and liturgy asserted by the great refomers abroad, and the most glorious and royal martyr the late King his opinion and suffrage for them. Published by a private gentleman for the publique good.</title>
            <author>Peirce, Edmund, Sir, d. 1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1032_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208951</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867867</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867867</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168904</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90361)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168904)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 153:E1032[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The English Episcopacy and liturgy asserted by the great refomers abroad, and the most glorious and royal martyr the late King his opinion and suffrage for them. Published by a private gentleman for the publique good.</title>
                  <author>Peirce, Edmund, Sir, d. 1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho. Leach, for Henry Seile, over against St. Dunstans Church, in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Sir Edmund Peirce.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 14".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168904:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ENGLISH EPISCOPACY AND LITURGY Aſſerted by the Great Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers abroad, AND The moſt Glorious and ROYAL MARTYR The Late KING His Opinion and Suffrage for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by a Private Gentleman for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Leach,</hi> for <hi>Henry Seile,</hi> over againſt St.
<hi>Dunſtans Church,</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="episcopacy" type="assertion">
               <pb facs="tcp:168904:2"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168904:2"/>
               <head>The Engliſh EPISCOPACY AND LITURGY ASSERTED.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Government is as neceſſary to the preſervation of the Church, as preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel was to the plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, is apparent by the Apoſtles practice, who no ſooner had conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Province, City, or any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of Perſons, but preſently left it in the hands of ſome faithful overſeers, to dreſſe, tend and water, till it grew up to ſuch a perfection as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Spouſe of Chriſt; And in all ſuch perfect and ſetled Churches, That there ought to be, three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Orders and Degrees in the paſtoral charge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<hi>viz.</hi> Biſhop, Prieſt or Presbyter, and Deacon, is ſo fully and abundantly Aſſerted and Proved, by ſo many able Pens, upon occaſion of the late differences in point of Church Diſcipline, and the ſame is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168904:3"/>become ſo known and manifeſt a Truth, eſpecially to the Learned, Solid, and Iudicious, that it cannot but be believed that thoſe of any conſiderable Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Ingenuitie, who chiefly oppoſed it, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main now very well ſatisfied in that particular, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed very cleer and apparent to knowing and impartial Iudgements, That Government by Biſhops ſuperior to Presbyters, is of Apoſtolical inſtitution; and this as fully to be made good, by Eccleſiaſtical Records, as it is poſſible for any Truth to be that way demonſtrated: Nor doth the Canon of the Sacred Scripture it ſelf, depend upon more undoubted and unqueſtionable verity and demonſtration.</p>
               <p>And although the abſolute and diſtinct precept of Chriſt himſelf for it, is not ſo cleerly to be Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; Yet his own ſuperiority to the twelve Apoſtles, and Theirs, to the ſeventy Diſciples, is ſuch an exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Copy of Biſhop, Prieſt or Presbyter, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, in the Government and Diſcipline of the Church, as that it was Tranſcribed in the very next Age (witneſs <hi>Ignatius,</hi> St. <hi>Johns</hi> Contemporary) and allowed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Eſteem and Honour; the Biſhops as Chriſt, the Presbyters as the Apoſtles, and Deacons as the Seventy. Nor is ſuperiority in Order leſſe cleerly A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical by the example and practice of themſelves, who when <hi>Judas</hi> had fell from the orb and dignity, he firſt moved in, They by the direction of the Sacred Spirit, aſſumed <hi>Matthias</hi> from an inferior, to a ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Order amongſt them; The Hierarchy of the Church in Government, being derivative as it were from God himſelf, and the ſame in Character and Repreſentation which he is pleaſed to exerciſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Bleſſed in Heaven.</p>
               <p>That therefore which ſome of a more unſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable nature and diſpoſition, though beaten out of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168904:3"/>all holds, for the Divine right of their <hi>Geneva</hi> Platform, yet loath to depart with that Claſſical, nay Parochial ſupremacy, and more than Lordſhip, which they Phanſied themſelves ſo near the abſolute poſſeſſion of, make now the matter of their frequent converſe, in all companies, and upon all occaſions, is to extoll and magnifie the order and manner of the Diſcipline of the reformed Churches abroad, and (to allure and captivate vulgar apprehenſions) very much advance and preferre the ſame, before that which hath been ſo long and legally eſtabliſhed here in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> under Biſhops, and which hath rendred us ſo famous and flouriſhing a people and Nation through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world.</p>
               <p>Howbeit if you demand now, of ſuch an extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Forein order, what Church abroad it is, not governed by Biſhops, which he ſo much magnifies for its Diſcipline; And wherein the excellency of it's beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty lyes; He knows not where to fix, but is at a kind of loſſe preſently, and after a ſmall while, the paradox doth ſo puzzle him in its maintenance, and hunt him from one abſurdity to another, that in concluſion, he is fain to ſit down, wildred and benighted in the fogs and darkneſſe of his own brain and Intellect.</p>
               <p>The difference of Diſcipline amongſt the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches abroad, is very well known, how thoſe of the French differ, from the Scotiſh, the Scotiſh from the Flemings or Dutch, thoſe from the Switzers, and ſo others in like manner, and the neceſſity of ſome Churches to fit their Tapeſtry to their Rooms, <hi>viz.</hi> their Diſcipline, to the ſtate and condition they live in, is as notorious. And certainly the modeſty of that grave and excellent Prelate is much to be commended, who having fully proved the impoſition, or laying on of hands by the Biſhop, to be of moſt antient inſtitution
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168904:4"/>in the Chriſtian Church, uſeth theſe words, I write not here (ſaith he) to prejudice our neighbour Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; I dare not limit the extraordinaray operation of the holy Spirit, where the ordinary means is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without the fault of the perſons, God fed his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with Manna, ſo long as they were in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Neceſſity is a ſtrong pleader; Many reformed Churches live under Kings, and Biſhops, of another Communion; Others have particular neceſſitating reaſons, why they could not continue, nor introduce Biſhops, But it is not ſo with us, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The exigence of time, place, and perſons may poſſibly be with Divine pity beheld in all their preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial hindrances, provided that divine order and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution be duely obſerved.</p>
               <p>Another reverend Biſhop hath likewiſe as charitable an expreſſion; <note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Hall in his treatiſe of Epiſcopacy</hi>
                  </note> I muſt cordially reſpect (ſaith he) thoſe forein Churches, who have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and followed an outward form, which in every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect is moſt expedient and ſuitable to their condition; And again, another ſpeaks thus, Some plants thrive beſt in the ſhadow; where the form of Government without Biſhops agrees beſt with the conſtitution of ſome Common-wealth, we pray to God to give them joy in it, and pray them to ſay as much for us. <hi>Damus petimuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> viciſſim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe very charitable and moderate paſſages of the Church Prelates, and Biſhops, are the rather hinted (and very many more might be) to manifeſt the difference there is, between the ſpirits and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſuch, and thoſe of ſome other perſons, who condemn all as Heretical and Antichriſtian, and to be extirpated Root and Branch, which complies not in
<hi>Omni modo,</hi> to their judgement, or rather Phanſy, and that by an Oath or Covenant impoſed, not only
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168904:4"/>upon ſiterate perſons, but upon ſuch alſo, who were ſo far from underſtanding the depth of what they ſware, as that they were utterly ignorant whether the words <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> and <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which they covenant to extirpate, be <hi>Hebrew, Greek, Latin, French, Italian, &amp;c.</hi> or what other language, and yet cry down thoſe Prelates, for Lordly, Imperious, and Tyrannical.</p>
               <p>We have it as a common rumor amongſt us Gentlemen, and it is ſuppoſed it will not be denyed, that a Declaration, or Letters miſſive, were by ſome grave perſons in Aſſembly, addreſſed to the reformed Churches of <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and
<hi>Switzerland,</hi> with diverſe other Churches, and States, inviting their concurrence, and approbation, to what thoſe perſons had prevailed with Authority here to ordain and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point concerning Church Diſcipline, and the rooting out of Epiſcopal order, Prelacy, and the Liturgy, but the ſucceſſe we are told it had in all places, is ſo far from being bragged on, (which had it anſwered ſome expectations would no doubt have been exalted to no ſmall height) that it is ſcarce at all known whether there were ever any ſuch thing or not, but an <hi>Altum Silentium</hi> thought fitteſt in the buſineſſe. It is not I ſuppoſe ſo proper for me (I leave that to others, who as much more concerned, ſo doubtleſſe, more truly knowing particulars) to publiſh to the Nation what I have credibly heard; nor perhaps will it (as affairs now ſtand,) be taken well on any part to relate what I read in a modern grave and ſober Author, (a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber alſo of a forein eminent reformed Church) as an anſwer from that reformed Church, where at that time they muſt needs feed their Phanſy with the beſt and faireſt hopes of ſucceſſe every way anſwerable to their expectation; nor ſhall I recite other particulars I read likewiſe concerning that addreſſe, which it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168904:5"/>ſeems being printed, was ſent to no leſſe than ſeaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Churches and States beyond ſea; nor what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation that Author ſaith it had, and what cenſure, the Phraſe, the Latine, the Tenor and ends thereof met with in ſome places, Albeit as the ſaid Author af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, the ſame is divulged to the world in ſeveral languages, though ſo little known here amongſt us, and how the reſt to whom it was addreſſed received the ſame, themſelves it is ſuppoſed beſt know; And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, it would be a ſignal peece of Candor and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity in them, and what (in ſuch a conjuncture of time as this) would be moſt grateful and acceptable to the whole Kingdome, eſpecially ſuch as my ſelf Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate-Lay-gentlemen who hear of theſe things at a diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and ſometimes read what caſually comes to their hands, and would very gladly hear the truth of what opinion their brethren of the reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches abroad, had of their addreſſe, and of the extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Epiſcopacy and Liturgy here amongſt us.</p>
               <p>But leſt this may in vain he called for, it ſhall here be very faithfully though briefly hinted, what ſome of the moſt eminent and renowned ſort of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abroad (amongſt many others which may in a little time be collected and ſet forth likewiſe) thought and expreſſed themſelves concerning thoſe two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of Epiſcopacy and Liturgy, which for ſome ends, have of late been ſuch ponderous and heavy burthens, and ſuch grievous eye-ſores to ſome people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calvin,</hi> it is hoped is one, who is, <hi>Omni excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one major.</hi> And therefore fitteſt to lead the Van in this particular, who in an Epiſtle of his to Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<hi>Sadolet,</hi> ſpeaking of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſaith thus, Let them (ſaith he) eſtabliſh ſuch an Hierarchy, where the Biſhops having the dignity, reſuſe not to ſubmit
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168904:5"/>themſelvs to Chriſt, and depend on him, as their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly head, and refer themſeves to him, And let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain amongſt them ſuch a brotherly Society, which is not entertained but by the Bond of Truth; then if there be found any perſons who refuſe to reſpect ſuch a Hierarchy, with Reverence and Soveraign Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, I do acknowledge and confeſſe him worthy of all ſorts of Anathema. This for the Epiſcopal Order and Degree in general, and from the Pen of <hi>Calvin</hi> the ſuppoſed Grand Anti-Epiſcopiſt, me-thinks ſhould bear much ſway and credit with ſome men.</p>
               <p>That great Profeſſor at <hi>Geneva, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. Theolog.</hi>
                     </note> Iacobus Lectius,</hi> makes the Engliſh Biſhops ſuch true and lawful Biſhops as St. <hi>Paul</hi> writeth of to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus.</hi> And we deny not (ſaith he) but there hath been formerly ſuch Biſhops, and that there are ſome now; and that they elect ſuch now in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beza</hi> writes thus to Arch-biſhop <hi>Whitgift;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>March</hi>
1. 1591.</note> In my writings (ſaith he) touching the Eccleſiaſtical go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, I have oppoſed the Roman Hierarchy, but it was never in my intention to oppoſe the Polity of the Engliſh Church, or to deſire of you to conform your Church, according to the pattern of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian diſcipline; for whilſt the ſubſtance of your Doctrine is uniform with the Church of Chriſt, It may be lawful for us to differ in other matters accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the circumſtances of time, place, and perſons require, and as is avowed by the preſcription of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, and for this effect I deſire and hope that the ſacred and holy ſociety of your Biſhops will continue, and maintain for ever, their right and title in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That great Author of the Buckler of faith, expounding the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Article of the Churches of
<hi>France</hi> Confeſſion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168904:6"/>of faith, cleerly expreſſes the great regard and eſteem they have of their neighbour Churches, where the Biſhops have ſuperiority. And in his diſputations of Divinity in the univerſity of <hi>Sedan,</hi> one of his Theſes is this, We maintain that the Biſhops of <hi>England,</hi> after their converſion to the faith, and their abjuration of Papiſtry, were faithful ſervants of God, and ought not to forſake, neither the name nor Title of Biſhops.</p>
               <p>Where can it be made appear, that any of the Reformed Churches abroad ever quarrelled at this our Church, as Anti-Chriſtian, or ſhewed the leaſt regret againſt it, for retaining the Epiſcopal Order or Liturgy amongſt us? nay what high Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miums and Gratulations from many of them, may be produced of this our Church, and Condolements of their own Condition, that they are not ſo happy and bleſſed as we are, in that particular of their Church Government, Order, and Diſcipline.</p>
               <p>It may therefore well be deemed more than a hard Task to procure thoſe Churches, ſo far to decline their Reaſon and Charity, as to contradict all their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer profeſſions ſo frequently made upon all occaſions, and their Conſciences too, meerly to gratifie the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and intereſt of ſome perſons, who though they had then (as they thought at leaſt) a great eſteem and credit abroad, found themſelves as much miſtaken in their expectations in that particular, as they were er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous in the Marks and Characters of Anti-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſm.</p>
               <p>It is poſsible the French Churches were much looked upon, as examples for Regulating the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo much noyſed and talked on here amongſt us; It cannot therefore be amiſſe to hear what a Sober, Learned, and Solid Member of the Church there writes, and that with ſadneſſe enough for their infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and neceſsitated condition.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:168904:6"/> The beſt (ſaith he) that they were able to do, (having the Court and Clergy againſt them) in matters of Order and Diſcipline, was, to provide Paſtors, who ſhould teach purely, and leave them in a ſimple equality, there being no queſtioning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Governing, in times of perſecution, but to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and ſuffer; And it being a thing of danger and envy to erect New Degrees, which could not be done without quarrelling at them which were eſtabliſhed; Neceſsity (ſaith he) contributed to Prudence in that Reformation, the ſame being moſt commodious for their preſent State; and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly could there be found a more proper and fitting for a Church that lives under Magiſtrates of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Religion, and in ſuch expectation of thoſe who injoy the Eccleſiaſtical degrees to come in likewiſe into the Reformation; They by their hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and equal order keep themſelves in a State of obedience, proper and ready to ſubmit themſelves to their Dioceſans, when it ſhall pleaſe God to convert them, And that their Fathers choſe this equality not as in oppoſition to the degrees of the Clergy, but as a way to diſpoſe them, and as a Plank ready to invite their Biſhops to paſſe over to the Reformation, and ſo receive them into their charge; We are not offended at the Degrees of the Clergy, nor their Revenues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This paper is intended to be very brief, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe great lights of the reformed Churches are only now mentioned, there being many others produceable to the ſame purpoſe, who very highly magnifie and extoll both our Government by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and alſo the Liturgical order and manner of our Divine worſhip to Almighty God, Concerning
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168904:7"/>which laſt particular, I ſhall likewiſe preſent the opinions of ſome of thoſe worthies of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, who upon occaſion have ſo declared their judgments thereupon, that the Framers of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory had ſurely very little cauſe to make the Nation believe, That by a long and ſad experience, (as is expreſſed in the Preface to that Directory) they find that the Engliſh Liturgy is offenſive to the Foreign reformed Churches, And that it is to anſwer the expectation of thoſe Churches that they reject it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf ſhall again lead the Van, upon this ſally likewiſe, for preſently after the compy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our Liturgy, by thoſe great Champions of the Engliſh Reformation, men of ſignal eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and renown, for wiſdom, piety, and learning, and ſome of them, upon that very ſcore and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, glorious for Martyrdome alſo; The ſame was ſent to Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> who wrote thus back to the then Protector of <hi>England,</hi> his Majeſty
<hi>Edw.</hi> the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. being then in minority.</p>
               <p>As for the form of Prayers, and Eccleſiaſtical Ceremonies I much approve, That they ſhould be eſtabliſhed, as a certain form from which it ſhall not be lawfull for the Paſtors to go in the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their charge, that ſo there may be proviſion made for ſimplicity, and the conſent of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches themſelves may more certainly appear, &amp; the extravagant levity of the affecters of novelty may be prevented; Here we ſee <hi>Calvin</hi> the great <hi>Zam Zum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim</hi> (as to ſome particulars) of the Framers of the Directory, cleerly aſſerting both that there ſhould be a certain form, from which it ſhould not be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to digreſſe, And alſo approving the book of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168904:7"/>Common Prayer ſent to him, and the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Orders and Ceremonies of the Engliſh Church.</p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Calvin</hi> in his notes upon the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> affords us a further and ample teſtimony of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of ſet forms of Prayer, and Liturgy; And in the Confeſſion preſented in the name of the Churches of <hi>France,</hi> to the Emperour and Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> he affirmeth thus, That every Church hath right to make Laws, Statutes, or Canons, and to eſtabliſh a common Policy or Diſcipline, And that obedience is owing to them, and thoſe that refuſe this, are to be accompted ſeditious and wilfull. Thus
<hi>Calvin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martin Bucer</hi> ſpeaking of the form of our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſervice or Liturgy, ſaith thus,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Script. Anglican.</hi> p. 445</note> I thank God who hath given you grace to reform thoſe ceremonies in ſuch a purity; For I have found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it which is not taken out of the word of God, or at leaſt is not contrary to it being rightly interpreted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gualter</hi> and <hi>Bullinger</hi> men who cannot be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their rank and due place of eminency amongſt thoſe of the Reformation, in a joynt Epiſtle of theirs wrote to ſome diſcontented Brethren here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> concerning the Diſcipline and Ceremonies of this our Church, ſay thus; That if any of the People perſwade themſelves, that thoſe things ſmell of Popery, Let them learn to know the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and let them be perfectly inſtructed; and that if the clamors of any raiſe up trouble among the multitude, let them beware, leſt in ſo doing, and provoking Authority, they draw not upon their necks a more heavy yoke.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:168904:8"/> 
                  <hi>Beza</hi> likewiſe in his Epiſtle <hi>Ad quoſdam An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicarum Eccleſiarum fratres,</hi> Speaking of the ſame ſubject matter, expreſſes himſelf fully to the ſame purpoſe, and tells them withall, That the Surpliſſe is not of ſuch importance to raiſe ſcruples in any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wearing of it, And ſo likewiſe for kneeling at the Sacrament, Muſick in Churches &amp; things of like nature, That they are matters of ſuch indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> f. 202. 112.</note> that they ſhould no ways be troubled at them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gilbertus</hi> a German, in a book of his long ſince written, propounds the Engliſh Liturgy, for a ſample of the antient forms uſed in the Church of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſaac Cauſabon</hi> that man of ſo great fame and learning, admires the care of our Engliſh Church for Antiquity, and Purity, and generally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims it in all his Epiſtles, That there was not any where elſe the like to be found, nor that he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hoped to ſee it in any place, till himſelf came hither into <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What the Church of <hi>Zeland,</hi> eſpecially the Wallachrian Claſſis returned in anſwer to ſome perſons, who addreſſed to them, is manifeſt enough, they not only approving of ſet &amp; preſcribed forms of publique Prayer, as tending much to edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but give reaſons of ſuch their approbation, from Scripture, and the practice of reformed Churches, and conclude it to be a preciſe ſingularity in thoſe who reject it.</p>
               <p>It would be endleſſe to relate the particular aſſertions of Foreign perſons, of choice ſincerity, and great learning, mayn Oppoſers likewiſe of the Roman rubbiſh and ſuperſtition, approving and applauding Liturgy, and ſet forms of Prayer for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168904:8"/>publique uſe in the ſervice of God, the whole Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an World indeed, in all ages (including Chriſt himſelf and his Apoſtles) and in all places, aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, approving, and advancing the ſame.</p>
               <p>And ſurely had ſome perſons but called to mind (for it is not poſſible to be imagined they ſhould be ignorant of it) what general approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Engliſh Liturgy and Ceremonies of this our Church received at <hi>Dort,</hi> by the Divines of <hi>Germany, France, Denmark, Swedeland,</hi> and <hi>Switzer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which appears in the Acts of that Synode, many of which Divines, as alſo ſome of our own then and there preſent, 'tis probable, may either yet be living at this day, or very lately Dead; I ſay had they been mindful of this, they would certainly have forborn to ſay there, where it is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique legible enough, That by long and ſad experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence they found, that the Engliſh Liturgy was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive to the foreign reformed Churches; for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly that is a very great error and miſtake, It being moſt manifeſt and notorious, that we are ſo far from giving them offence in that particular, that it ſeems they deſire nothing more earneſtly, than to be in the ſame condition with us, which appears by a Declaration made by ſome Divines of note and eſteem in foreign parts, and that but few years agoe, and ſince ſome of our late troubles here amongſt us firſt began, which <hi>inter alia</hi> ſpeaks thus.</p>
               <p>One day, when it ſhall pleaſe God to perfect, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Edit. a D. Jobanne Duraeo An.</hi> 1638.</note> and confirm Amity in theſe Churches, we may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by a univerſal Council and Conſent to form a certain Liturgy, which may be as a Symbole and Bond of Concord amongſt us. Some perſons, ('tis true) have made it a <hi>Malum Diſcordiae</hi> here; But we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168904:9"/>ſee, our neighbours look upon a Liturgy, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſet form of Prayer, to be as a Symbole and Bond of Concord to them.</p>
               <p>Nor indeed is there any thing more true, than That all the reformed Churches abroad have their certain forms of Prayers for their Publique and Sacred adminiſtrations, nor is it leſſe true, That many of the ſaid Churches have Biſhops likewiſe in full order and dignity, anſwerable and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent to thoſe of this our Church of <hi>England,</hi> as all thoſe Countries ſubject to the Crowns of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sweden;</hi> Almoſt throughout all
<hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> likewiſe, the Epiſcopal Order and Degree is kept up and preſerved, though under another name and Title, <hi>viz. Super-Intendents,</hi> and in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as in
<hi>Brene,</hi> the name of Biſhops ſtill remains; In the large and ample Territories of
<hi>Bohemia, Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> and <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> the Evangelical reformed Churches are Governed by <hi>Seniors,</hi> as they call them, who are in the ſame nature, quality, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and armed with the ſame power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for Church Government, as our Biſheps.</p>
               <p>To ſay nothing of thoſe Churches of <hi>Ruſsia, Grecia,</hi> and <hi>India,</hi> and the reſt of the world, whoſe Doctrine indeed we leſſe know what it is, than we do their Diſcipline, it being not unknown, that their Church Government there, is by Biſhops, both in quality and Title, ſo that it may well be deemed as a thing very improbable, that the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugners of Epiſcopacy and Liturgy here amongſt us at home, will ever be able to make it appear by all the Art or indeavours that can be uſed, That any approbation, countenance, or aſſiſtance to them in ſuch their deſign, will ever in any way or ſort be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168904:9"/>affoorded to them from abroad, eſpecially from any conſiderable place of the Reformation, who are ſo far from deſiring the glory of the Engliſh Church, heretofore ſo famous and flouriſhing in all reſpects whatſoever, and yeelding ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection ſafety and honour to all their reformed neighbours and allyes, in all parts and places, ſhould be any way darkened or ecclipſed, or its eminency and luſtre in any kind diminiſhed, or abated; That nothing (queſtionleſſe) hath been, is, or can be, greater matter of Sorrow and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolement to them, than the Ayms, Attempts and Deſires of ſome men; nor more Joy and Paſtime to our Romiſh Adverſaries, than to ſee the Sons and Members of that Church, heretofore ſo terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and dreadful to them, and their Uſurpations, rending and tearing out their Mothers Bowels, and all for controverſies of Government, Diſcipline, and Ceremony, and that without the leaſt ſhew of ought tending to any need or neceſſity whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p>Thus much for a taſt only, how the Reformed Foreign Palats have, and (without all doubt) ſtill do Relliſh that ſharpneſſe which hath here been u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, againſt that Government, Order, and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, which hath ſo long beautified and rendred glorious that Kings Daughter, our Church of <hi>England,</hi> and which had ſuch a beginning, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance and ſo firm and often repeated an eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment.</p>
               <p>And having made the precedent mention of the great joy and pleaſure which our Romiſh Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries (no doubt) take, at theſe differences here amongſt us, And ſince that ſome perſons (who
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168904:10"/>perhaps leaſt meant it) have indeed (which 'tis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped is now become cleer and manifeſt to them) but waged their War, and fought their Battails, wherein themſelves, by all their Learning and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, could never make ſo great an advance as of late years ſince our Troubles began; <hi>Let it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred,</hi> that upon the Reformed Compoſure of our Liturgy, the great quarrel then againſt it, was alwayes made by the Papiſts, which they ſet on foot, under ſeveral Modes and Guizes, ſometimes complaining of that, which they called Craft and Subtlety in our Reformers, in their ſeeming com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with them, and how politique they were to order things ſo, as might in ſhew ſeem no great departure from them, in their publique worſhip and ſervice of God, yet really and indeed they had thereby given them the far more deadly wound, and ſuch, whereof it would be very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult for them ever to work out a recovery.</p>
               <p>Sometimes in down right terms they fell upon it, being ſo reformed and reduced to pure Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; Inſomuch that <hi>John Ould</hi> in <hi>Queen Maries</hi> dayes, and many others eminent Aſſertors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, publiquely wrote againſt them in Defence of it. And Arch-Biſhop
<hi>Cranmer,</hi> made a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Challenge, that if he might be permitted to take to him
<hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and 4. or 5. more, he would enter the Liſts with any Papiſts living, and defend the Book to be perfectly agreable to the word of God, and the ſame in effect which had been uſed in the Church of God for 1500 yeers.</p>
               <p>And in thoſe fiery dayes of <hi>Queen Mary,</hi> when the uſe of it was interdicted, it was frequently bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as an haeretical peice condemned by Roman
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168904:10"/>Authority, in the ſame Fire with ſuch as ſuffered Martyrdom, for aſſerting that and other Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rins and uſages of our Church, of which there is amongſt others, this memorable Record in the Acts and monuments of our Church, That one <hi>Iohn Hullyer</hi> fellow of Kings College in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, who being at the ſtake, A book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-Prayer amongſt others, was thrown into the fire to him, and happened to fall between his hands, which he received with the greateſt joy that could poſſibly be expreſſed by him, and read in it till the flame and ſmoak hindred his ſight, and then he clapt it to his breaſt, cloſely embrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and with elevated hands and devout pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers he yeelded up the ghoſt.</p>
               <p>Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> before mentioned (who amongſt other things objected, for ſuch aſſerting the Liturgy <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuffered Martyrdom likewiſe by the Papiſts,) in his letters publiſhed by <hi>Myles Coverdale,</hi> laments it, as the moſt cruel and ſevere piece of perſecution and tyranny towards him, that they would not ſuffer him to have the uſe of the Common-Prayer book in Priſon.</p>
               <p>What troubles at <hi>Frankfort,</hi> aroſe to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, flying thither for refuge, and by whoſe fomentation, and incouragement they befell, and continued amongſt them, is manifeſt enough, and how learnedly and unanſwerably the Engliſh Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, and every part thereof, was there maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by them againſt all Oppoſers whatſoever, is as manifeſt likewiſe.</p>
               <p>Nor can it be thought a difficult matter to gueſſe who privately and obliquely excited and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, <hi>Hacket, Coppinger,</hi> and <hi>Arthington,</hi> in <hi>Q.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168904:11"/>Eliz.</hi> time, and many others which might be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, who though under a quite contrary pretence, and zealous ſhew of deteſting Popery and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet acted the part of the ſtouteſt and moſt dangerous Champions to introduce it, as that Age could any way have afforded.</p>
               <p>Certainly that Liturgy, and form of Divine worſhip, muſt needs be very neer the Golden Mean, and no leſſe bleſſed and happy in its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure, whoſe fate it hath alwayes been, to be crucified between two grand contrary oppoſing partyes, and ſtigmatized with their ſeveral Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, the one branding it for Novelty and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, the other for Superſtition and Popery.</p>
               <p>And this, no doubt but, was fore-ſeen by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, whoſe great wiſdome and piety in their labours therein can never be enough Admired, and Celebrated, they ſtoutly and piouſly flinging off all both in that, and the doctrine of the Church, which had any tincture or ſavour of Superſtition or Popery in it, and with as little outward alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (which was their ſingular wildome and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion) as ſuch an affair could poſſibly admit, keeping and Retaining all recommended and practiſed by pure Antiquity; And which doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe is as free and cleer from any true charg of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, as any period expreſſed in the writings of ſuch who have laid that heavy charg upon it, they knowing well that Liturgy, Moderation, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and as neer a compliance as poſſibly might be admitted without Sin, was a far better and more probable way to convert Papiſts, and confirm Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, than Sequeſtration, Directory, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination by Presbyters only; Nor did they forget
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168904:11"/>that there were many thouſands of Pariſhes in this Realm and Nation, where there is no ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Divine inſpiration, to be relyed on; But that in all probability, many of the Minſters will not be alwayes able publiquely to ſpeak, as in the preſence of Angels, which the woeful experience of the late times hath abundantly verifyed to us. To ſay nothing of the flat and empty Nonſence, and hydeous Blaſphemies, the expreſſion whereof (had they been duly collected in all places) would ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fill a volume, and are far more fit to be buryed in utter Oblivion, than that it ſhould arrive at the ears of Poſterity, to accuſe the Raſhneſſe and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſuch perſons, who would needs thruſt out the unwearyed Labours, Piety, and Wiſdom of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Glorious Martyrs, and inſtead thereof, bring in, only the extemporary volatile expreſſions of particular Perſons (how able ſoever) into the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Worſhip and Service of Almighty God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing the ſtanding Treaſures of the Church for help and aſſiſtance, and making uſe of ſuch Coyn, as is ſo far from having any ſtamp upon it, as that it is perpetually to be new run, and mynted; Not remembring, or duly conſidering at leaſt, that there were in the Apoſtles times, divers gifts, and every Miniſter had no promiſe to ſucceed in all, But one in one, and another in another gift, yet all by the ſame spirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is believed that Doctor <hi>Preſton</hi> is not without a pretious Memory amongſt the chief of ſuch who have oppoſed Liturgy; his obſervation therefore, may not unduly be here hynted, which was this; That whilſt thoſe who in oppoſition to ſet forms, require the Miniſter to conceive a Prayer for the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168904:12"/>Congregation, They conſider not, that the whole Congregation is as much ſtynted and bound to a ſet form, <hi>viz.</hi> of thoſe words, which the Miniſter conceives and pronounces, as if he read them out of a Book; Nor will the preſcription of the matter at all help out, in this caſe of unpremeditated and extemporary prayer, as ſome perhaps may think; for if that be flown too for refuge and cure of obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities; That remedy proves every whit as bad as the Diſeaſe, the Spirit being in that caſe ſtynted likewiſe (the only thing in pretence to be avoyded) The matter preſcribed, every way as much hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring and obſtructing that, which they call the Freedome of the Spirit in Prayer, as if the very words themſelves were confined and preſcribed alſo.</p>
               <p>And whereas this ſacred form of Prayer, and ſervice of Almighty God, and ſome other rites and uſages of the Church, have been ſo much and often accuſed to ſavour of Popery, and to keep thoſe of the Romiſh faith in hopes and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our return to them: The quite contrary Argument may certainly with far more reaſon be thence aſſumed and taken up; It being our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with the Antient Church of the pureſt times, and not with them, which we practiſed; And our retaining and keeping thoſe antient forms and Rites, being a more probable way of gaining them to us, than any hopes they could thence have of our coming in to them; Nor could ſuch comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ours with them, ſo far as any way we law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully might, ſignifie ought elſe to any rational Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, But that we meant thereby (which queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſs is the truth) to leave them without all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168904:12"/>if they did not anſwer us in the like compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with us in what they might, And ſo reſtore the ſo much deſired Peace and Union of <hi>Chriſtendom;</hi> And of this certainly the Jeſuits and others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them were in ſuch dread and fear, that it might be effectually operative upon the moderate ſort of Papiſts here amongſt us, that none were more mortally hated by them than ſuch as were chief upholders, favourers and ſupporters of that Antient Government, Order, Rites and Service, and the ſtrict rules and preſcriptions thereof, which they ſo much feared and were offended at for the cauſe and reaſon aforeſaid. And therefore if <hi>Romes Master-Peice</hi> (a book appointed by the long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to be ſet out) ſay true, The late Glorious King, and the then Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> Dr.
<hi>Laud,</hi> whoſe wayes and courſe in this particular they ſaw ſo croſſe and oppoſite to their deſignes, and putting them into ſuch frights of loſing all their game, prey, and Mart here, were in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular deſtined by them to the ſlaughter, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (queſtionleſs) whom they not only utterly deſpaired ever to gain to them, but were very like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to endanger the ruine of the whole Roman Cauſe. Others there were too, They knew, who ſeemed in Noyſe indeed, far their greater Enemies, yet we never had the leaſt murmure of any ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign againſt any of them, though it cannot but be believed, ſuch were truly and really their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies likewiſe; They knew too well what uſe to make of their Zeal and diſcontent; And doubtleſſe excellent good uſe might have been made againſt the Romiſh deſigns of ſuch-their Zeal and fervour, if they would have permitted it to come under a due
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168904:13"/>and prudent management, by thoſe who had juſt and lawful authority over them.</p>
               <p>I promiſed brevity, and therefore but one word more is to be Craved, and although by me but Craved, yet it is ſuch, as may juſtly clayman Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Regard from, and a convincing likewiſe to, the moſt wilful and obdurate whatſoever in theſe particulars of Epiſcopacy and Liturgy. It is a word from a King, Their own King, their own dying King, nay Their Martyred King, Martyred chiefly upon this very ſcore and accompt, to preſerve E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy and Liturgy to the People; whom God had committed to his charge.</p>
               <p>How dear and pretious to all ſober and pious Proteſtants, is the memory of thoſe Prelates of our Church, who firſt compyled the Liturgy for its uſe? with what high Honour and Renown did we all along (till this laſt wild and ſudden Tempeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe amongſt us) exalt and magnify their names and memories, from one age to another ſince their Martyrdome, who willingly and cheerfully laid down their lives in juſtification of what they had therein done, againſt their Roman Adverſaries, And in a Fiery Chariot paſſed from Earth to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to receive the reward and Crown of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for ſuch their pious and eminently uſefull, and truly profitable Labours for the Church of God? how greedily did we catch each word they ſpake, and with what care and diligence were they preſerv'd in the grand Record of the Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of the Church (a Book I hope no way ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to exception from thoſe to whom this is chiefly intended) And what Impreſſions have they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes made, in the minds of the ſober Readers,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168904:13"/>ſuch as muſt needs keep out all thoughts from Breſts not totally poyſoned with malicious preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and Suſpition, of any Popiſh or Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Tyncture to have its Reſidence in thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. And if ſo?</p>
               <p>Shall then the words, the laſt words, upon this Subject, of a Dying King of Martyrs, receive any ſlight, or loſe their due effect? which as written with the Seraphick Quill, of one of thoſe Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Attendants, upon the higheſt Divine Majeſty (for ſuch is its Solidity and Elegancy) deſerves a Regiſtry (with reverence be it ſpoken) in the acts and monuments of the Church Triumphant in Heaven, where that glorious Royal Martyr enjoys his due place, and hath reached and put on that Iluſtrious, Immortal, and Immarceſſible Crown prepared for him there, having deſpiſed and depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited an earthly one here, rather than deprive his people of that benefit, which he well knew, they could not but receive from the divine Order, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and Function of Epiſcopacy; And the moſt excellent diſcipline and devotion of our refined Liturgy and publique ſervice of Almighty God. It being notoriouſly known, that if he would have ſacrificed the Church, he needed not have been <hi>The Churches Sacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let a Retreat be made from theſe crude lines, and a Liſten given to thoſe Charming drops from a Royal pen Seraphically enabled whilſt on earth, and now ſo tranſcendently qualified, as not to be reached ſo much as in any imagination, which frail humanity is in the leaſt ſort capable of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="episcopacy" type="resolution">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:168904:14"/>
               <head>Concerning Epiſcopacy, his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al words are theſe.</head>
               <p>TOuching the Government of the Church by Biſhops the common Jealouſy hath been, that I am earneſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute to maintain it, not ſo much out of piety, as policy and reaſon of State.</p>
               <p>Wherein ſo far indeed reaſon of State doth induce me to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove that government above any other, as I find it impoſſible for a Pince to preſerve the State in quiet, unleſſe he hath ſuch an influence upon Church-men, and they ſuch a dependence on him, as may beſt reſtrain the ſeditious exorbitancies of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters tongues; Who with the Keys of Heaven, have ſo far the Keys of Peoples hearts, as they prevail much with their Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to let in; or ſhut out, both Peace and Loyalty.</p>
               <p>So that I being (as King) intruſted by God, and the Laws, with the good both of Church and State, I ſee no reaſon I ſhould give up, or weaken by any change, that power and influence which in right and reaſon I ought to have over both.</p>
               <p>The moving Biſhops out of the Houſe of Peers (of which I have elſewhere given an account) was ſufficient to take off any ſuſpition, that I encline to them for any uſe to be made of their Votes in State-affairs: Though indeed I never thought any Biſhop worthy to ſit in that Houſe, who would not Vote ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Conſcience.</p>
               <p>I muſt now in Charity be thought deſirous to preſerve that Government in its right conſtitution, as a matter of Religion;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168904:14"/>wherein both my judgment is fully ſatisfied, that it hath of all other the fulleſt Scripture-grounds, and alſo the conſtant pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of all Chriſtian Churches, till of late years the tumultua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs of People, or the factiouſneſs and pride of Presbyters, or the covetouſnes of ſome States and Princes, gave occaſion to ſome mens w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts to invent new models, and propoſe them under the ſpecious titles of <hi>Chriſts Government, Scepter, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> the better to ſerve their turns to whom the change was beneficial.</p>
               <p>They muſt give Me leave, having none of their temptations to invite Me to alter the Government of Biſhops, (that I may have a title to their Eſtates,) not to believe their pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed grounds, to any new ways contrary to the full and conſtant teſtimony of all Histories, ſufficiently convincing unbyaſſed men; That as the Primitive Churches were undoubtedly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by the Apoſtles and their immediate ſucceſſors, the firſt and beſt Biſhops, ſo it cannot in reaſon or charity be ſuppoſed, that all Churches in the world ſhould either be ignorant of the rule by them preſcribed, or ſo ſoon deviate from their divine and holy pattern: That ſince the firſt age, for <hi>1500.</hi> years, not one example can be produced of any ſettled Church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were many Miniſters, and Congregations, which had not ſome Biſhop above them, under whoſe juriſdiction and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment they were.</p>
               <p>Whoſe conſtant and univerſal practice agreeing with ſo large and evident Scripture-directions, and examples, are ſet down in the Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and
<hi>Titus,</hi> for the ſettling of that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, not in the perſons only of
<hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> but in the ſucceſſion (The want of Government being that which the Church can no more diſpence with, in point of well-being, than the want of the Word and Sacraments, in point of being.)</p>
               <p>I wonder how men came to look with ſo envious an eye upon Biſhops power and authority, as to over-ſee both the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal uſe of them, and Apoſtolical conſtitution: which to me ſeems no leſſe evidently ſet forth as to the main ſcope and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168904:15"/>of thoſe Epiſtles, for the ſettling of a peculiar Office, Power, and Authority in them, as Preſident Biſhops above others, in point of Ordination, Cenſures, and other acts of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſcipline; than thoſe ſhorter Characters of the qualities and duties of <hi>Presbyter-Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> are deſcribed in ſome parts of the ſame Epiſtles, who in the latitude and community of the name were then, and may now not improper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be called Biſhops, as to the over-ſight and care of ſingle Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, committed to them by the Apoſtles, or thoſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Biſhops, who (as <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi>) ſucceeded them in that ordinary power; there aſſigned overlarger diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in which were many Presbyters.</p>
               <p>The humility of thoſe firſt Biſhops, avoyding the eminent title of Apoſtles, as a name in the Churches ſtile appropriated from its common notion <hi>(of a Meſſenger, or one ſent)</hi> to that ſpecial dignity which had extraordinary call, miſſion, gifts, and power immediately from Chriſt, they contented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the ordinary titles of Biſhops, and Presbyters, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till uſe, (the great arbitrator of words, and maſter of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) finding reaſon to diſtinguiſh by a peculiar name thoſe perſons, whoſe power and office were indeed diſtinct from and above all other in the Church, as ſucceeding the Apoſtles in the ordinary and conſtant power of governing the Churches, the honour of (whoſe name they moderately, yet commendably declined,) all Chriſtian Churches (ſubmitting to that ſpecial authority,) appropriated alſo the name of Biſhop, without any ſuſpition or reproach of arrogancy, to thoſe who were by Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical propagation rightly deſcended and inveſted into that higheſt and largeſt power of governing even the moſt pure and Primitive Churches, which without all doubt had many ſuch holy Biſhops, after the pattern of <hi>Timothy</hi> and
<hi>Titus,</hi> whoſe ſpecial power is not more cleerly ſet down in thoſe Epiſtles, (the chief grounds and limits of all Epiſcopal claim, as from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right,) than are the Characters of thoſe perilous times, and thoſe men that make them ſuch, who not enduring ſound Doctrine, and clear teſtimonies of all Churches practice, are moſt perverſe Diſputers, and proud Uſurpers againſt true E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168904:15"/>Who, if they be not Traytors and Boaſters, yet they ſeem to be very covetous, heady, high-minded, inordinate and fierce, lovers of themſelves, having much of the form, little of the power of godlineſſe.</p>
               <p>Who by popular heaps of weak, light, and unlearned Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſeek to over-lay and ſmoother the pregnancy and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that power of Epiſcopal Government, which beyond all equivocation and vulgar fallacy of names, is moſt convincing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet forth both by Scripture, and all after Hiſtories of the Church.</p>
               <p>This I write, rather like a Divine than a Prince, that poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may ſee (if ever theſe papers be publick) that I had fair grounds both from Scripture-Canons, and Eccleſiaſtical exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, whereon my judgment was ſtated for Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
               <p>Nor was it any policy of State, or obſtinacy of Will, or partiality of Affection, either to the Men or their Function, which fixed Me: who cannot in point of worldly reſpects be ſo conſiderable to Me, as to recompence the injuries and loſſes, I and My deareſt relations with My Kingdoms have ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and hazarded, chiefly at firſt upon this quarrell.</p>
               <p>And not only in Religion, of which, Scripture is the eſt rule, and the Churches Univerſal practice the beſt commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but alſo in right reaſon, and the true nature of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it cannot be thought that an orderly Subordination among Prebyters, or Miniſters, ſhould be any more againſt Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, than it is in all ſecular and Civil Governments, where parity breeds Confuſion and Faction.</p>
               <p>I can no more believe, that ſuch order is intonſiſtent with true Religion, than good features are with beauty, or numbers with harmony.</p>
               <p>Nor is it likely that God, who appointed ſeveral orders, and a Prelacy in the Government of his Church, among the Jewiſh
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168904:16"/>Prieſts, ſhould abhor or forbid them among Chriſtian Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; who have as much of the principles of ſchiſm and diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as other men; for preventing and ſuppreſſing of which, the Apoſtolical wiſdom (which was divine) after that Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were multiplyed ſo many Congregations, and Presbyters with them, appointed this way of Government, which might beſt preſerve order and union with Authority.</p>
               <p>So that I conceive, it was not the favor of Princes, or am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of Presbyters, but the wiſdom and piety of the Apoſtles, that firſt ſetled Biſhops in the Church, which Authority they conſtantly uſed and enjoyed in thoſe times which were pureſt for Religion, though ſharpeſt for Perſecution.</p>
               <p>Nor that I am againſt the managing of this Preſidency and Authority in one man, by the joynt Counſel and conſent of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Presbyters, I have offered to reſtore that, as a fit means to avoid thoſe Errors, Corruptions, and Partialities, which were incident to any one man; Alſo to avoid Tyranny, which becomes no Chriſtians, leaſt of all Church-men; beſides it will be a means to take away that burthen and <hi>odium</hi> of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, which may lye too heavy on one mans Shoulders, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I think it formerly did on the Biſhops here.</p>
               <p>Nor can I ſee what can be more agreeable both to Reaſon and Religion, than ſuch a frame of Government which is Paternal, not Magiſterial, and wherein not only the neceſſity of avoiding Faction and Confuſion, Emulations and Contempts, which are prone to ariſe among equals in power and function, but alſo the differences of ſome Miniſters gifts, and aptitudes for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment above others, doth invite to imploy them, in referernce to thoſe abilities wherein they are eminent.</p>
               <p>Neither is this judgement of mine, touching Epiſcopacy, any preoccupation of opinion, which will not admit any oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt it: It is well known I have endeavoured to ſatisfie My ſelf in what the chief patrons for other ways can ſay againſt this, or for theirs: And I find they have, as far leſs of Scripture grounds, and of reaſon, ſo for examples and practice of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:168904:16"/>Church, or teſtimonies of Hiſtories, they are wholly destitute, wherein the whole ſtream runs ſo for Epiſcopacy, that there is not the leaſt rivulet for any others.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe obtruded examples of ſome late reformed Churches (for many retain Biſhops ſtill) whom neceſſity of times and affairs rather excuſeth than commendeth for their inconformity to all Antiquity; I could never ſee any reaſon why Churches orderly reformed and governed by Biſhops, ſhould be forced to conform to thoſe few, rather than to the Catholike ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of all Antient Churches, which needed no Reformation: And to thoſe Churches at this day, who governed by Biſhops in all the Chriſtian world, are many more than Presbyterians or Independents can pretend to be; All whom the Churches in my three Kingdoms lately governed by Biſhops, would equalize (I think) if not exceed.</p>
               <p>Nor is it any point of wiſdom or charity, where Chriſtians differ, (as many do in ſome points) there to widen the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and at once to give all the Chriſtian world (except a handfull of ſome Proteſtants) ſo great a ſcandal in point of Church-Government; Whom though you may convince of their errours in ſome point of Doctrine, yet you ſhall never perſwade them, that to compleat their Reformation they muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſert, and wholly caſt off that Government, which they and all before them have ever owned as Catholick, Primitive, and Apoſtolical: So far, as never Schiſmaticks, nor Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks (except thoſe Arrians) have ſtrayed from Unity, and Conformity of the Church in that point; ever having Biſhops above Presbyters.</p>
               <p>Beſides, the late general approbation and ſubmiſſion to this Government of Biſhops, by the Clergy, as well as the Laity of theſe Kingdoms, is a great confirmation of My Judgment; and their inconſtancy is a great prejudice againſt their Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; I cannot in charity ſo far doubt of their learning or inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, as if they underſtood not what heretofore they did; or that they did conform contrary to their Conſciences; So that their facility and levity is never to be excuſed, who, before e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:168904:17"/>the point of Church-Government had any free and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial debate, contrary to their former oathes and practice, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their obedience to the Laws in force, and againſt My conſent, have not only quite cryed down the Government by Biſhops, but have approved and incouraged the violent and moſt illegal ſtripping all the Biſhops, and many other Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, of all their due Authority and Revenues, even to the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away, and utter alienation of thoſe Church-lands, from any Eccleſiaſtical uſes: So great a power hath the ſtream of times, and the prevalency of parties over ſome mens judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; of whoſe ſo ſudden and ſo total change, little reaſon can be given, beſides the <hi>Scots</hi> Army comming into
<hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the folly of theſe men will at l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt puniſh it ſelf, and the Deſertors of Epiſcopacy will appear the greateſt enemies to, and betrayers of their own intereſt: For Presbytery is never ſo conſiderable or effectual, as when it is joyned to, and crowned with Epiſcopacy. All Miniſters will find as great a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in point of thriving, between the favour of the People, and of Princes, as plants do between being watered by hand, or by the ſweet and liberal dews of Heaven.</p>
               <p>The tenuity and contempt of Clergy-men, will ſoon let them ſee what a poor carcaſe they are, when parted from the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of that head, to whoſe ſupremacy they have been ſworn.</p>
               <p>A little moderation might have prevented great miſchiefs; I am firm to Primitive Epiſcopacy, not to have it extirpated, if I can hinder it. Diſcretion without Paſſion might eaſily reform, whatever the ruſt of Times, or indulgence of Laws, or corruption of Manners have brought upon it. It being a groſſe vulgar errour, to impute to, or revenge upon the function, the faults of times, or perſons; which ſeditious and popular principle, and practice, all wiſe men abhor.</p>
               <p>For thoſe ſecular additaments and ornaments of Authority, Civil honour, and Eſtate which my Predeceſſors, and Chriſtian Princes in all Countries have annexed to Biſhops and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:168904:17"/>I look upon them but as juſt rewards of their learning and piety, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are fit to be in any degree of Church-Government; alſo enablements to works of Charity and Hoſpitality, meet ſtrengthenings of their Authority in point of reſpect, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, which in peaceful times is hardly payed to any Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours by the meaſure of their Vertues, ſo much, as by that of their Eſtates: Poverty and Meaneſſe expoſing them and their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to the contempt of licentious minds, and manners, which perſecuting times much reſtrained.</p>
               <p>I would have ſuch men Biſhops, as are moſt worthy of thoſe incouragements, and beſt able to uſe them: if at any time My Judgement of men failed, My good intention made my error venial; And ſome Biſhops, I am ſure I had, whoſe learning, gravity, and piety, no men of any worth or forehead can deny: But, of all men, I would have Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, eſpecially the Governors, to be redeemed from that vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar neglect, which (beſides an innate principle of vitious op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, which is in all men againſt thoſe that ſeem to reprove, or reſtrain them) will neceſſarily follow both the Presbyterian parity, which makes all Miniſters equal; and the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent inferiority, which ſets their Paſtors below the People.</p>
               <p>This for my judgement touching Epiſcopacy, wherein (God knows) I do not gratify any deſign or paſſion with the leaſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of truth.</p>
               <p>And now I appeal to God above, and all the Chriſtian world, whether it be juſt for Subjects, or pious for Chriſtians, by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and infinite indignities, with ſervile reſtraints to ſeek to force Me their King and Soveraign, as ſome men have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to do, againſt all theſe grounds of my Judgement, to conſent to their weak and divided novelties.</p>
               <p>The greateſt Pretender of them deſires not more than I do, That the Church ſhould be governed, as Chriſt hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in true Reaſon, and in Scripture; of which I could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee any probable ſhew for any other ways: who either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſeves with the examples of ſome Churches in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:168904:18"/>and ſolitude, when one Presbyter might ſerve one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, in a City or Country; or elſe they deny theſe moſt evident Truths, that the Apoſtles were Biſhops over thoſe Presbyters they ordained, as well as over the Churches they planted; and that Government being neceſſary for the Churches well-being, when multiplyed and ſociated, muſt alſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily deſcend from the Apoſtles to others, after the example of that power and ſuperiority they had above others; which could not end with their perſons; ſince the uſe and ends of ſuch Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſtill continue.</p>
               <p>It is moſt ſure, that the pureſt Primitive and beſt Churches flouriſhed under Epiſcopacy; and may ſo ſtill, if ignorance, ſuperſtition, avarice, revenge, and other diſorderly and diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al paſſions had not ſo blown up ſome mens minds againſt it, that what they want of Reaſons or Primitive Paterns, they ſupply with violence and oppreſſion; wherein ſome mens zeal for Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Lands, Houſes, and Revenues, hath ſet them on work to eat up Epiſcopacy: which (however other men eſteem) to Me is no leſſe Sin, than Sacrilege, or a Robbery of God (the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of all we have) of that portion, which devout minds have thankfully given again to him, in giving it to his Church and Prophets; through whoſe hands be graciouſly accepts even a cup of cold water, as a libation offered to himſelf.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, as to My particular engagement above other men, by an Oath agreeable to My Judgement, I am ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obliged to preſerve that Government, and the Rights of the Church.</p>
               <p>Were I convinced of the unlawfulneſſe of the Function, as Antichriſtian (which ſome men boldly, but weakly calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e) I could ſoon with Judgement break that Oath, which erroniouſly was taken by Me.</p>
               <p>But being dayly by the beſt diſquiſition of truth, more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the Reaſon and Religion of that to which I am ſworn; How can any man that wiſheth not My Damnation, perſwade Me at once to ſo notorious and combined Sins, of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:168904:18"/>and Perjury? beſides the many perſonal Injuſtices I muſt do to many worthy men, who are as legally inveſted in their eſtates, as any who ſeek to deprive them; and they have by no Law been convicted of thoſe crimes, which might forfeit their Eſtates and Livelyhoods.</p>
               <p>I have often wondred how men pretending to tenderneſs of Conſcience, &amp; Reformation, can at once tell Me, that my Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-Oath binds Me to conſent to whatſoever they ſhall propound to Me (which they urge with ſuch violence) though contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to all that Rational and Religious freedom which every man ought to preſerve, and of which they ſeem ſo tender in their own Votes: Yet at the ſame time, theſe men will needs perſwade Me, That I muſt and ought to diſpenſe with, and roundly break that part of my Oath, which binds me (agreeable to the beſt light of Reaſon and Religion I have) to maintain the Government, and legal Rights of the Church. 'Tis ſtrange My lot ſhould be valid in that part, which both My ſelf, and all men in their own caſe, eſteem injurious &amp; unreaſonable, as being againſt the very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral eſſential liberty of our Souls; Yet it ſhould be invalid, &amp; to be broken in another clauſe, wherein I think My ſelf juſtly obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged both to God and Man.</p>
               <p>Yet upon this Rack chiefly have I been held ſo long, by ſome mens ambitious Covetouſneſs, and ſacrilegious Cruelty, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing (with Me) both Church and State, in Civil diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, till I ſhall be forced to conſent, and declare, that I do approve, what (God knows) I utterly diſlike, and in My Soul abhor; as many wayes highly againſt Reaſon, Juſtice, and Religion; and whereto, if I ſhould ſhamefully, and diſhonourably give My conſent; yet ſhould I not by ſo doing, ſatisfie the divided Intereſts and Opinions of thoſe Parties, which contend with each other, as well as both againſt Me and Epiſcopacy.</p>
               <p>Nor can My late condeſcending to the <hi>Scots</hi> in point of Church-government, be rightly objected againſt Me, as an inducement for Me, to conſent to the like in my other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms: For it ſhould be conſidered, that Epiſcopacy was not ſo
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:168904:19"/>rooted and ſetled there, as 'tis here; nor I (in that reſpect) ſo ſtrictly bound to continue it in that Kingdom, as in this: For what I think in My Judgement beſt, I may not think ſo abſolutely neceſſary for all places, and at all times.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall impute My yielding to them, as My failing and Sin, I can eaſily acknowledge it; but that is no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to do ſo again, or much worſe; I being now more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced in that point: Nor indeed hath My yielding to them been ſo happy and ſucceſſeful as to incourage Me to grant the like to others.</p>
               <p>Did I ſee any thing more of Chriſt, as to Meekneſs, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Order, Charity, and Loyalty, in thoſe that pretend to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther modes of Government, I might ſuſpect My Judgement to be biaſſed, or foreſtalled with ſome prejudice and wonted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of opinion; But I have hitherto ſo much cauſe to ſuſpect the contrary in the manners of many of thoſe men, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not from them gain the leaſt Reputation for their new wayes of Government.</p>
               <p>Nor can I find that in any Reformed Churches (whoſe pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns are ſo cryed up, and obtruded upon the Churches under My Dominion) that either Learning, or Religion, Works of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Charity, have ſo flouriſhed beyond what they have done in my Kingdoms (by Gods bleſſing) which might make Me believe either Presbytery or Independency have a more benign influence upon the Church, and mens hearts and lives, than E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy in its right conſtitution.</p>
               <p>The abuſes of which deſerve to be extirpated, as much as the uſe retained; for I think it far better to hold to Primitive and uniform Antiquity, than to comply with divided Novelty.</p>
               <p>A right Epiſcopacy would at once ſatisfie all juſt deſires and intereſts of good Biſhops, humble Presbyters, and ſober People; ſo as Church-affairs ſhould be managed neither with tyranny, parity, nor popularity; neither Biſhops ejected, nor Presbyters deſpiſed, nor People oppreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:168904:19"/> And in this integrity both of My Judgement and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, I hope God will preſerve me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="episcopacy" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITATION.</head>
               <p>FOr thou, O LORD, knoweſt my uprightneſſe and tenderneſſe; as thou haſt ſet Me to be a Defender of the Faith, and a Protector of thy Church, ſo ſuffer Me not by any violence, to be over-born againſt my Conſcience.</p>
               <p>Ariſe, O LORD, maintain thine own Cauſe, let not thy Church be deformed, as to that Government, which derived from thy Apoſtles, hath been retained in pureſt and primitive times, till the Revenues of the Church became the object of ſecular envy, which ſeeks to rob it of all the encouragements of Learning and Religion.</p>
               <p>Make Me, as the good Samaritan, compaſſionate, and helpful to thy afflicted Church; which ſome men have wounded and robbed; others paſſe by without regard, either to pity, or relieve.</p>
               <p>As my power is from thee, ſo give Me grace to uſe it for thee.</p>
               <p>And though I am not ſuffered to be Maſter of my other Rights as a King, yet preſerve Me in that liberty of Reaſon, love of Religion, and thy Churches welfare, which are fixed in my Conſcience as a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>Preſerve, from Sacrilegious Invaſions, thoſe temporal bleſſings, which thy providence hath beſtowed on thy Church for thy glory.</p>
               <p>Forgive their ſins and errors, who have deſerved thy juſt permiſſion, thus to let in the wilde Boar, and ſubtile Foxes, to waſte and deform thy Vineard, which thy right hand hath planted, and the dew of Heaven ſo long watered to a happy and flouriſhing eſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:168904:20"/> O let me not bear the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amous brand to all Poſterity, of being the firſt Chriſtian King in this Kingdom, who ſhould conſent to the oppreſſion of thy Church, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of it; whoſe errours I would rather, with <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> cover with ſilence, and reform with meekneſſe, than ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their perſons, and ſacred Functions, to vulgar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
               <p>Thou, O LORD, ſeeſt how much I have ſuffered with, and for thy Church; make no long tarrying, O my God, to deliver both me and it, from unreaſonable men, whoſe counſels have brought forth, and continue ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent confuſions, by a precipitant deſtroying the antient boundaries of thy Churches peace; thereby letting in all manner of errours, ſchiſms, and diſorders.</p>
               <p>O thou God of order, and of truth, in thy good time, abate the malice, aſſwage the rage, and confound all the miſchievous devices, of thine, mine, and thy Churches enemies.</p>
               <p>That I, and all that love thy Church, may ſing praiſes to thee, and ever magnifie thy ſalvation, even before the ſons of men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="liturgy" type="resolution">
               <head>Concerning the Liturgy, his Royal words are theſe.</head>
               <p>IT is no news to have all Innovations uſhered in with the name of Reformations in Church, and State, by thoſe, who ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to gain reputation with the Vulgar for their extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary parts, and piety, muſt needs undo whatever was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſettled never ſo well and wiſely.</p>
               <p>So hardly can the pride of thoſe that ſtudy Novelties, allow former times any ſhare or degree of wiſdom or godlineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:168904:20"/> And becauſe matter of Prayer and Devotion to God juſtly bears a great part in Religion (being the Souls more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate converſe with the Divine Majeſty) nothing could be more plauſible to the People, than to tell them, they ſerved God amiſſe in that point.</p>
               <p>Hence our publick Liturgy, or Forms of conſtant Prayers muſt be (not amended, in what upon free and publick adviſe might ſeem to ſober men inconvenient for matter or manner, to which I ſhould eaſily conſent, but) wholly caſhiered and aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and after many popular contempts offered to the Book, and thoſe that uſed it according to their Conſciences, and the Laws in force, it muſt be crucified by an Ordinance, the better to pleaſe either thoſe men, who gloried in their extemporary vein, and fluency; or others, who conſcious to their own formality in the uſe of it, thought they fully expiated their ſin of not uſing it aright, by laying all the blame upon it, and a total re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ection of it as a dead letter, thereby to excuſe the deadneſſe of their hearts.</p>
               <p>As for the matter contained in the Book, ſober and learned men have ſufficiently vindicated it againſt the cavils and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of thoſe, who thought it a part of piety to make what prophane objections they could againſt it, eſpecialy for Popery and Superſtition; Whereas no doubt the Liturgy was exactly conformed to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> And this by all Reformed Churches is confeſſed to be moſt ſound and Orthodox.</p>
               <p>For the manner of uſing Set and preſcribed Forms, there is no doubt but that wholſom words being known and fitted t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mens underſtandings are ſooneſt received into their hearts, and apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to excite and carry along with them judicious and fervent affections.</p>
               <p>Nor do I ſee any reaſon why Chriſtians ſhould be weary of a well compoſed Liturgy (as I hold this to be) more than of all other things, wherein the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtancy abates nothing of the excellency and uſefulneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:168904:21"/> I could never ſee any reaſon why any Chriſtian ſhould abhor or be forbidden to uſe the ſame forms of Prayer, ſince he prays to the ſame God, believes in the ſame Saviour, profeſſeth the ſame Truths, reads the ſame Scriptures, hath the ſame Duties upon him, and feels the ſame dayly Wants for the moſt part, both inward and outward, which are common to the whole Church.</p>
               <p>Sure we may as well before-hand know what we pray, as to whom we pray, and in what words, as to what ſenſe; when we deſire the ſame things, what hinders we may not uſe the ſame words? our appetite and diſgeſtion too may be good when we uſe, as we pray for, <hi>Our daily bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some men, I hear, are ſo impatient not to uſe in all their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions their own invention and gifts, that they not only diſuſe (as too many) but wholly caſt away and contemn the
<hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> whoſe great guilt is, that it is the warrant and ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal pattern of all ſet Liturgies, in the Chriſtian Church.</p>
               <p>I ever thought that the proud oſtentation of mens abilities for invention, and the vain affectations of variety for expreſſions, or in publick Prayer, or in any ſacred adminiſtrations, merits a greater brand of ſin, than that which they call Coldneſſe and Barrenneſſe: nor are men in thoſe novelties leſſe ſubject to formal and ſuperficial tempers (as to their hearts) than in the uſe of conſtant Forms, where not the words, but mens hearts are too blame.</p>
               <p>I make no doubt but a man may be very formal in the moſt extemporary variety: and very fervently devout in the moſt wonted expreſſions: nor is God more a God of Variety, than of Conſtancy; nor are conſtant Forms of Prayers more likely to flat and hinder the Spirit of Prayer, and Devotion, than unpreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated and confuſed variety, to diſtract and loſe it.</p>
               <p>Though I am not againſt a grave, modeſt, diſcreet and humble uſe of Miniſters gifts, even in publique, the better to fit and excite their own, and the peoples affections to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſions: yet I know no neceſſity why private and ſingle
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:168904:21"/>abilities ſhould quite juſtle out, and deprive the Church of the joynt abilities and concurrent gifts of many learned and godly men; ſuch as the Compoſers of the Service-Book were; who may in all reaſon be thought to have more of gifts and graces enabling them to compoſe with ſerious deliberation and concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent adviſe, ſuch Forms of Prayers, as may beſt fit the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es common wants, inform the Hearers underſtanding, and ſtir up that fiduciary and fervent application of their spirits (wherein conſiſts the very life and ſoul of Prayer, and that ſo much pretended Spirit of Prayer) that any private man by his ſolitary abilities can be preſumed to have: which, what they are many times (even there, where they make a great noiſe and ſhew) the affectations, emptineſſe, impertinency, rudeneſſe, confuſions, flatneſſe, levity, obſcurity, vain and ridiculous repetitions, the ſenſleſſe, and oft times blaſphemous expreſſions (all theſe burthened with a moſt tedious and into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable length) do ſufficiently convince all men, but thoſe who glory in that Phariſaick way.</p>
               <p>Wherein men muſt be ſtrangely impudent, and flatterers of themſelves, not to have an infinite ſhame of what they ſo do and ſay, in things of ſo ſacred a nature, before God and the Church, after ſo ridiculous, and indeed, profane a manner.</p>
               <p>Nor can it be expected, but that in duties of frequent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, as Sacramental adminiſtrations, and the like, which are ſtill the ſame; Miniſters muſt either come to uſe their own Forms conſtantly, which are not like to be ſo ſound or compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of the nature of the duty, as Forms of publick compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; or elſe they muſt every time affect new expreſſions when the ſubject is the ſame; which can hardly be preſumed in any mans greateſt ſufficiencies not to want (many times) much of that compleatneſſe, order, and gravity, becomming thoſe duties; which by this means are expoſed at every celebration to every Miniſters private infirmities, indiſpoſitions, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, diſorders, and defects, both for judgment and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</p>
               <p>A ſerious ſenſe of which Inconvenience in the Church, una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:168904:22"/>following every mans ſeveral manner of officiating, no doubt, firſt occaſioned the wiſdom and piety of the Antient Churches, to remedy thoſe miſchiefs, by the uſe of conſtant Liturgies of Publick compoſure.</p>
               <p>The want of which I believe this Church will ſufficiently feel, when the unhappy fruits of many mens ungoverned ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and confident defects, ſhall be diſcovered in more errours, ſchiſms, diſorders, and uncharitable diſtractions in Religion, which are already but too many, the more is the pity.</p>
               <p>However, if violence muſt needs bring in, and abett thoſe innovations, (that men may not ſeem to have nothing to do) which Law, Reaſon, and Religion forbids, at leaſt to be ſo obtruded, as wholly to juſtle out the publick Liturgie.</p>
               <p>Yet nothing can excuſe that moſt unjuſt and partial ſeverity of thoſe men, who either lately had ſubſcribed to, uſed and maintained the ſervice book; or refuſed to uſe it, cried out of the rigour of Laws and Biſhops, which ſuffered them not to uſe the Liberty of their Conſciences in not uſing it.</p>
               <p>That theſe men (I ſay) ſhould ſo ſuddenly change the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy into a Directory, as if the Spirit needed help for inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though not for expreſſions; or as if matter preſcribed did not as much ſtint and obſtruct the Spirit, as if it were cloathed in, and confined to fit words: (So ſlight and eaſy is that Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerdemain which will ſerve to delude the Vulgar.)</p>
               <p>That further they ſhould uſe ſuch ſeverity, as not to ſuffer without penalty, any to uſe the Common-Prayer-Book pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely, although their Conſciences bind them to it, as a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Piety to God, and Obedience to the Laws.</p>
               <p>Thus I ſee, no men are prone to be greater Tyrants, and more rigorous exacters upon others to conform to their illegal Novelties, than ſuch, whoſe pride was formally leaſt diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the obedience of lawful Conſtitutions, and whoſe licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:168904:22"/>humors moſt pretended Conſcientious liberties, which freedom, with much regret they now allow to Me, and My Chaplains, when they may have leave to ſerve Me, whoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities even in their extemporary way, comes not ſhort of the others, but their modeſty and learning far exceeds the moſt of them.</p>
               <p>But this matter is of ſo popular a nature, as ſome men knew it would not bear learned and ſober debates, leſt being convinced by the evidence of Reaſon, as well as Laws, they ſhould have been driven either to ſin more against their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; by taking away the Liturgy: or to diſpleaſe ſome facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people, by continuing the uſe of it.</p>
               <p>Though I believe they have offended more conſiderable men, not only for their numbers and eſtates, but for their weighty and judicious piety, than thoſe are, whoſe weakneſſe or gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe they ſought to gratifie, by taking it away.</p>
               <p>One of the greateſt faults ſome men found with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer-Book, I believe was this, That it taught then to pray ſo oft for Me; to which Petitions they had not Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty enough to ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> nor yet Charity enough to forbear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and even Curſings of Me in their own Forms, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of praying for Me.</p>
               <p>I wiſh their Repentance may be their only puniſhment; that ſeeing the miſchiefs which the diſuſe of Publique Liturgies hath already produced, they may reſtore that credit, uſe, and Reverence to them, which by the antient Churches were given to Set Forms of ſound and wholſom words.</p>
               <p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div n="liturgy" type="meditation">
                           <head>MEDITATION.</head>
                           <p>ANd thou O LORD, which art the ſame God, bleſſed for ever: whoſe mercies are full of variety, and yet of conſtancy; thou denyeſt us not a new and freſh ſenſe of our old and dayly wants; nor deſpiſeſt renewed affections joyned to conſtant expreſſions.</p>
                           <p>
                              <pb n="44" facs="tcp:168904:23"/> Let us not want the benefit of thy Churches united and well-adviſed Devotions.</p>
                           <p>Let the matters of our Prayers be agreeable to thy will, which is alwayes the ſame, and the fervency of our Spirits to the motions of thy holy Spirit in us.</p>
                           <p>And then we doubt not, but thy ſpiritual perfections are ſuch, as thou art neither to be pleaſed with affected Novelties for matter or manner, nor offended with the pious conſtancy of our petitions in them both.</p>
                           <p>Whoſe variety or conſtancy thou haſt no where either forbidden or commanded, but left them to the piety and prudence of thy Church, that both may be uſed, neither deſpiſed.</p>
                           <p>Keep men in that pious moderation of their judgments in matter of Religion; that their ignorance may not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend others, nor their opinion of their own abilities, tempt them to deprive others of what they may lawfully and devoutly uſe, to help their infirmities.</p>
                           <p>And ſince the advantage of Error conſiſts in novelty and variety, as Truths in unity and conſtancy: Suffer not thy Church to be peſtered with errors, and deformed with undecencies in thy ſervice, under the pretence of variety, and novelty. Nor to be deprived of truth, unity, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, under this fallacy, That conſtancy is the cauſe of formality.</p>
                           <p>LORD keep us from formal Hypocriſie in our own hearts, and then we know that praying to thee, or prayſing of thee (with <hi>David</hi> and other holy men) in the ſame forms, cannot hurt us.</p>
                           <p>Give us wiſdome to amend what is amiſſe within us, and there will be leſſe to mend without us.</p>
                           <p>Evermore defend and deliver thy Church from the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of blind zeal, and ov-erbold devotion.</p>
                           <p>
                              <pb n="45" facs="tcp:168904:23"/> 
                              <hi>SIlence after this, beſt becomes humanity, No fit additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to this All-Comprehenſive brevity can poſſibly be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by any Pen, in the hand of a Mortal; yet ſince Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption hath dared to inſert theſe few words, after ſuch divinely-inſpired, and tranſcendently elegant and pithy lines; What better amends can be made, than to cloze up this Rude breach, by a ſecond Retreat, And liſtening again, to what (as to the particulars before treated of) that Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Quill left Ingraven as his laſt words amongſt many others, his truly Royal and moſt eminently-Pious and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Inſtructions to his Son, then Heir apparent of all his Earthly Crowns and Dominions, and now our moſt Dear and Dread Lord and Soveraign.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>ABove all, I would have You, as I hope You are already, well grounded and ſetled in your Religion: The beſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of which, I have ever eſteemed <hi>that of the Church of England,</hi> in which you have been educated: Yet I would have your own Judgement and Reaſon now ſeal to that ſacred bond which education hath written, that it may be judiciouſly your own Religion, and not other mens cuſtome or tradition, which you profeſs.</p>
               <p>In this I charge You to perſevere, as comming neareſt to Gods Word for Doctrine, and to the Primitive examples for <hi>Government,</hi> with ſome little amendment, which I have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhere expreſsed and often offered, though in vain. Your fixation in matters of Religion will not be more neceſſary for your Souls, than your Kingdomes peace, when God ſhall bring you to them.</p>
               <p>For I have obſerved, that the Devil of Rebellion, doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly turn himſelf into an Angel of Reformation; and the old Serpent can pretend new Lights: When ſome mens Conſciences accuſe them for Sedition and Faction, they ſtop its mouth with the name and noiſe of Religion; when Piety pleads for Peace and patience, they cry out Zeal.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:168904:24"/> So that, unleſſe in this point You be well ſetled, you ſhall never want temptations to deſtr Yoy ou and Yours, under preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Reforming matters of Religion; for that ſeems, even to worſt men, as the beſt and moſt auſpicious beginning of their worſt deſigns.</p>
               <p>Where, beſides the Novelty which is taking enough with the Vulgar, every one hath an affectation, by ſeeming forward to an outward Reformation of Religion, to be thought zealous; hoping to cover thoſe irreligious deformities, whereto they are conſcious, by a ſeverity of cenſuring other mens opinions or actions.</p>
               <p>Take heed of abetting any Factions, or applying to any publick Diſcriminations in matters of Religion, contrary to what is in your Judgement, <hi>and the Church well ſettled, &amp;c.</hi> You may never expect leſſe of Loyalty, Juſtice, or Humanity, than from thoſe who ingage into Religious Rebellion; Their intereſts are alwayes made Gods, under the colours of Piety, ambitions policies march, not only with greateſt ſecurity, but applauſe, as to the populacie; you may hear from them <hi>Jacobs</hi> voyce, but you ſhall feel they have <hi>Eſaus</hi> hands.</p>
               <p>Nothing ſeemed leſſe conſiderable than the Presbyterian Faſhion in <hi>England,</hi> for many years; ſo complyant they were to publique publick order: nor was their party great
<hi>either Church</hi> or State, as to mens judgements: But as ſoon as Diſcontent drave men into Sidings (as ill humours fall to the diſaffected part, which cauſes inflamations) ſo did all, at firſt, who affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any Novelties, adhere to that Side, as the moſt remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſpecious note of difference (then) in point of Religion.</p>
               <p>All the leſſer Factions at firſt were officious Servants to Presbytery their great Maſter: till time and military ſucceſſe diſcovering to each their peculiar advantages, invited them to part ſtakes, and leaving the joynt ſtock of uniform Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pretended each to drive for their Party the trade of profits and preferments, to the breaking and undoing not only of the Church and State, but even of Presbytery it ſelf, which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and hoped at firſt to have ingroſſed all.</p>
               <p>In theſe two points, the preſervation of <hi>Eſtabliſhed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Laws,</hi> I may (without Vanity) turn the reproach of My ſuffrings as to the Worlds cenſure, into the honour of a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:168904:24"/>kind of Martyrdome, as to the teſtimony of My own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: The Troublers of My Kingdoms having nothing elſe to object againſt me but this, that I prefer
<hi>Religion and Laws Eſtabliſhed</hi> before thoſe alterations they propounded.</p>
               <p>I have, You ſee, conflicted with different and oppoſite Factions (for ſo I muſt needs call and count all thoſe, that act not in any conformity to the Lawes <hi>eſtabliſhed, in Church</hi> and State) no ſooner have they by force ſubdued what they coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their Common Enemy, (that is, all thoſe that adhered to the Lawes, and to Me) and are ſecured from that fear, but they are divided to ſo high a rivalry as ſets them more at defiance againſt each other, than againſt their Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts.</p>
               <p>Time will diſſipiate all Factions, when once the rough horns of private mens covetous and ambitious deſigns, ſhall diſcover themſelves; which were at firſt wrapt up and hidden under the ſoft and ſmooth pretenſions of Religion, Reformation and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: As the Wolf is not leſſe cruel, ſo he will be more juſtly hated, when he ſhall appear no better than a Wolf under Sheeps cloathing.</p>
               <p>If You never ſee My face again, and God will have Me buried in ſuch a barbarous Impriſonment and obſcurity, (which the perfecting ſome Mens deſigns require) wherein few hearts that love Me are permitted to exchange a word, or a look with Me; I do require and entreat You as Your Father and Your King, that You never ſuffer Your heart to receive the leaſt check againſt, or diſaffection from the true <hi>Religion eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Churc of England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I tell You, I have tryed it, and after much ſearch and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſputes, have concluded it to be the beſt in the world; not only in the Community, as Chriaſtin, but alſo in the special notion, <hi>as Reformed</hi> keeping the middle way between the pomp of ſuperſtitions Tyranny, and the meaneſſe of of fantaſtique A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</p>
               <p>Not but that (the draught being excellent as to the main, both for Doctrine and Government, in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) ſome lines, as in very good figures, may haply need ſome ſweetning, or poliſhing; which might here have eaſily been done by a ſafe and gentle hand; if ſome mens precipitancy had
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:168904:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>not violenly demanded ſuch rude alterations, as would have quite deſtroyed all the beauty and proportions of the whole.</p>
               <p>The ſcandal of the late Troubles, which ſome may object, and urge to You againſt the Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſhed in <hi>England,</hi> is eaſily Anſwered to them, or Your own thoughts in this, That ſcarce any one who hath been a Beginner, or an active Proſecutor of this late War againſt the Church, the Laws, and Me, either was, or is a true Lover, Embracer, or Practiſer of the Proteſtant Religion, eſtabliſhed in <hi>England:</hi> which neither gives ſuch rules, nor ever before ſet ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, ſome heretofore had the boldneſſe to preſent threatning Petitions to their Princes and Parliaments, which others of the ſame Faction, (but of worſe ſpirits) have now put in execution: but let not counterfeit and diſorderly Zeal abate Your value and eſteem of true Piety, both of them are to be <hi>known by their fruits;</hi> the ſweetneſſe of the Vine and Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree is not to be deſpiſed, though the Brambles and Thorns ſpould pretend to bear Figs and Grapes, thereby to rule over the Trees.</p>
               <p>And if God will have diſloyalty perfected by My deſtruction, let My memory ever, with My name live in You, as of Your Father that loves You, and once a King of three flouriſhing Kingdoms, Whom God thought fit to honour, not only with the Scepter and Government of them, but alſo with the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many indignities, and an untimely death for them; While I ſtudied to preſerve the <hi>rights of the Church,</hi> the power of the Laws, the honour of My Crown, the privilege of Parliaments, the liberties of My People, and My own Conſcience, which I thank God is dearer to Me than a thouſand Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>Keep You to true principles of piety, virtue, and honour, You ſhall never want a Kingdom.</p>
               <p>I pray God bleſs You, and eſtabliſh Your Kingdoms in righteouſneſs, Your Soul <hi>in true Religion,</hi> and Your honour in the love of God and Your people.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
